Have you noticed who it is who can't
stop talking about the private credit
bust maybe crisis? The big bankers.
Jamie Dimon, perfect example, he of
cockroach fame. He seems only too happy
to share his negative opinions and
insights with anyone in the media.
Goldman Sachs's David Solomon just
recently very loudly, very publicly
reminded everyone the credit cycle has
not been repealed.
You know who it is we haven't heard a
word from?
Life insurance executives. Those who
write the annuities, the retirement
plans. And that already tells you
something important about this cycle.
2008 was about big banks. 2026
is about big insurance.
As the saying goes, it's a dog that
hasn't barked. The real systemic danger
isn't JP Morgan or Deutsche Bank, it's
Prudential or MassMutual. And that
doesn't necessarily mean either of those
companies are high risk of failing.
They're simply exposed. They're they're
neck deep in private credit and the
reaching for yield which built it. Life
insurers these days are mainly about
managing retirements, which is why their
bubble behavior the past couple years
has been the most bubbly as we'll see
here. In the grand scheme, insurers have
both enabled and largely funded that
very bubble. And that raises several
uncomfortable critical questions. After
all, even the Treasury Department is
talking with state insurance regulators
about this very topic. So in this video,
we're going to dive deep into where this
came from and why insurance companies
are at the forefront. Then we're going
to investigate the exposures and the
exposures to exposures. Third, after
doing so, that's going to illuminate
where these dangers are coming from. And
yes, it does involve repo, collateral,
and as always, the hidden leverage that
comes with it. They keep telling us
there isn't much leverage. Well, as it
turns out, there is and repo is not
unexpectedly right there in the middle
of it.
Finally, we'll discuss what all of this
might actually mean for insurance
companies, for the state of the private
credit bust, for retirement plans and
annuities. After all, if it was
insurance companies who had the biggest
shovel when shoveling all that cash into
the bubble,
they stand to have a lot to lose, and so
does the overall system. So, we're going
to go into why 2026
is the year of big insurance, not big
banks.
It's one of the most interesting, let's
call it, parts of the private credit
story right now. Just who is doing all
the talking and who isn't. Now, we know
what Blue Owl is. Lady Macbeth has been
protesting loudly for over 6 months now.
And in that whole time, just bringing
even more attention to the bubble and
the bubble behavior. And who has the owl
been shouting most at? Why, the big
bankers, like Jamie Dimon or David
Solomon at Goldman. The former guy at
Goldman, Blankfein. He said the same
thing. Our friend over at Deutsche Bank,
Mr. Turman. The big bankers are all over
this thing, which is a huge clue about
what it is you really need to pay
attention to. It's not the next Lehman
Brothers. I mean, Jamie Dimon, in his
letter to JP Morgan shareholders last
week, basically spilled the beans.
Quote, "However this plays out," talking
about the private credit bust, "it
should be expected that at some point
insurance regulators will insist on more
rigorous ratings or markdowns, which
will likely lead to demands for more
capital." Insurance
regulators.
That's because insurance companies and
pension funds are right in the middle of
this, particularly the former. Think
about what an insurance business really
is. It takes in cash payments today in
exchange for promises to pay out
tomorrow. And for life insurance firms
most of all, those promises aren't
necessarily on a policy holder's death.
Life insurance these days is much more
about retirement assets. Yes, the
annuity business. So, So, workers pay
their money today in exchange the life
insurer promises to make periodic
payments in the future. And in order to
be able to make those payments, not to
mention pocket some profits along the
way, the life insurance company has to
generate some dependable returns. High
enough that they can meet their future
obligations plus put some money in their
pocket. But, they also don't want to
take on too much risk because too many
credit losses mean they won't be able to
live up to their contractual
obligations. Now, these financial firms
are in effect the very archetype for
reach for yield. They need to generate
good numbers and are constantly under
pressure to keep them coming. And if
they think the downside for taking on a
little more risk is minimal, why not
move just one more notch or two further
down the risk spectrum? Go from double A
to single A or maybe even triple B plus.
What's the danger? More and more return
with no discernible increase potential.
At least that's the thought process.
Moreover, as I'll show you here, reach
for yield isn't just about the asset
classes that are being put into these
portfolios. It's also how they're being
managed. And yes, I am talking about
leverage. And yes, that does mean repo
because it always means repo. So, there
is far more leverage that is hidden
within these portfolio strategies than
everyone seems to realize. Certainly
more than anyone is willing to admit
from inside the industry. It is that
potentially toxic combination under
reach for yield, the riskier assets with
more short-term borrowing to further
juice the returns, that is the biggest
downside to all of this. And as far as
those risks are concerned, we've talked
about this repeatedly in the context of
private credit specifically. Bubble
behavior doesn't just apply to the
portfolio managers like Blue Owl or KKR
and any of the other ones that we've
been talking about. It definitely
applies and then some to the ultimate
asset owners, in this case, the
insurance companies.
What is a Eurodollar University
membership? It's where understanding the
monetary world isn't a mystery, it's a
method. If you're serious about your
financial education and you want clarity
in a world of volatility and
misunderstanding,
this is for you.
Mainstream education has left so many
gaps on the most foundational concepts,
making sense of everything is
practically impossible otherwise. With
our memberships, we'll fill in
everything that you've been missing.
Whether you're starting out or
sharpening your edge, our membership
scale with your goals. At Eurodollar
University, we teach you about how money
really works so that you can evaluate
fundamentals and make grounded
decisions. With a Eurodollar University
membership, you get a comprehensive
library of foundational and advanced
lectures, in-depth case studies, and
real-world analyses, live Q&A sessions,
regular updates on macro trends, and
even some central bank policies. And
most important, how to interpret
critical derivative market signals you
will not find anywhere else.
You can't be in a position to succeed if
you don't know how it all really works
and fits together. So, if you're ready
to explore, master monetary systems both
past and future with structure, clarity,
and confidence, click the link in the
description to visit
eurodollar.university/memberships
to join us today.
We see this in every cycle throughout
history. Bubble behavior is really human
nature, and human nature is undefeated.
We go through this every single time.
People believe that risks are low
because the numbers all look good. The
situation seems to prove and validate
the idea. Risks are low because they
appear to be low, and then all of a
sudden, they're not low because they
were never low. We just didn't realize
it, or in many cases, most cases, nobody
wanted to realize it. Subprime mortgage
default rates, for example, they were
really low throughout the years before
the 2007 blow-up. Even during the
dot-com recession in 2001,
they didn't really pick up, which
\quote} "proved" to investors there
weren't heavy risks to buying packages
of subprime mortgages. That's how cycles
work. Everything appears too good to be
true for a very long period, convincing
everyone to take even more risk, and
then suddenly, seemingly out of nowhere,
it all comes crashing down. But, it
isn't out of nowhere. Risks and losses
just don't show up in any of the past
numbers, especially in the recent past.
So, everyone just assumed the risks
weren't there when they always were. For
the past little while, default rates
looked terrific, but that's not going to
last. In fact, we're already seeing a
material pick-up in stress, which
indicates 2026 truly might be the year
the cycle goes full-blown cycle. This is
the whole thing behind the liquidity
problems and investor withdrawals. And
insurance companies, they appear to be
right in the thick of it, and they
increasingly are.
In fact, that's the least controversial
part of this. We know insurance
companies are heavily, heavily exposed.
And to be clear, we're not talking about
Progressive, Geico, or State Farm. We're
talking about the life insurance
companies, the annuity writers,
MassMutual and Prudential, Guardian,
those types of things. So, let's let's
put some numbers on it, which is, you
know, rough numbers, not exactly all
that hard to do.
Let's start with something that Reuters
pulled up just 2 weeks ago. \quote}
"Private credit accounts for 35%, 35% of
total US insurer investments, close to a
quarter of UK insurer investments. More
worryingly, insurers affiliated with
private credit firms hold an estimated
$1 trillion in assets acquired through
those relationships, and the exposure to
private credit losses will fall
disproportionately on US pension funds
and retail savers who have purchased
life annuities from these insurers. And
Dromel's Gallo said he wouldn't dismiss
the private credit woes as non-systemic
risk simply by comparing it with the
2008 subprime crisis, which was driven
by extended housing leverage through
what was termed collateralized debt
obligations. It really was collateral
and repo, but either way, this is a
different animal with different
contagion channels, he said, referring
to how leverage is pumped up in later
stages in private credit by insurers.
Similar process, different players. Now,
over at S&P Global, that outfit put
together some more estimates which show
these private placements, the kind of
private credit products we're talking
about, bonds and securities that come
out of the process, they were nearing a
quarter, 1/4 of their total bond
exposures. Now, these estimates, that's
not the proportion of their total
assets, but it's still a hefty piece and
it it largely jives with just went over.
But not only that, look at what insurers
have been doing over the past four now
five years, they've forgot how to grow.
They've been absolutely reaching for
yield from 18% according to S&P Global
to 23%
in just those four years, the same years
that economic fundamentals kept getting
materially worse, even if loss and
default rates remained low, therefore
obscuring the overall deterioration.
Also obscuring it has been the lack of
underwriting as we as we're getting more
and more familiar with. And there's
more. Here's another one which shows not
only are insurance companies reaching
for yields and assets, they're getting
more and more directly directly involved
in creating those private credit assets
to begin with. This is from the ABF
Journal. McKinsey's Global Private
Markets Review 2025 reported that
insurance-linked platforms now account
for approximately 25% of global private
credit assets under management up from
15% in 2021. So, a 10 percentage point
increase in these same forgot how to
grow deteriorating lack of underwriting
years. Insurance companies allocation to
alternative credit strategies grew at a
22% compound annual growth rate over the
past 4 years, the worst possible 4 years
to be doing something like that, to be
reaching for yield in this to this
extent. But, insurance companies,
they're not just reaching for yield,
they're basically addicted to the
private credit industry and what it
promised to provide.
And because of that addiction, it
obviously led to, like I said, bubble
behavior. That meant in many ways
cutting corners, including on
ratings and ratings agencies, private
letters, rating shopping, all sorts of
bad bubbly behavior that we've seen
before.
Now, the Wall Street Journal reported
just a week ago that the US Treasury
Department is alarmed about what's going
on with insurers and private credit. The
amount of bubble behavior
rationalizations
does appear to be excessive. Let's go to
the journal. The Treasury Department
wants to talk to state insurance
commissioners about the private credit
loans piling up in insurers portfolios.
Those state regulators have been keeping
some of their thoughts to themselves.
That's another clue. The National
Association of Insurance Commissioners,
the organization for regulators from
every state, in 2024 published a
bombshell study revealing that the
ratings on insurers private credit
investments were routinely inflated.
This past May, the group pulled the
report from its website and said it
needed to clarify its findings as if
that wasn't suspicious enough. Now,
about 419 billion of that debt carries a
so-called private letter rating and it's
probably a lot more than that. In some
ways, such a rating resembles what the
ratings firms provide for publicly
traded bonds. The firm issuing or
packaging the debt pays a ratings
company to assign a grade based on the
likelihood the borrower will repay it.
But unlike bond ratings, private letter
grades are available only to the debt's
issuer and investors, and this is
something we've seen too much of. And
like I said, it's probably more
pervasive than what we know. Now, the
BIS, for example, it had raised alarms
on private letters, which is nothing
more than rating shopping. You go to a
ratings agency, give them some sample of
your assets, and if the agency doesn't
give you the rating you want, you simply
go to the next one until eventually you
find someone willing to put their stamp
on it. And because it's a private
letter, this is why it's called a
private letter, no one knows you went to
other agencies who would have given you
a bad grade. All this adds even more,
let's call it intrigue, to the private
credit industry, the information
asymmetry. But with insurance companies,
they're right there at the top. They
feel they have to reach for yield and
for years have been doing bubbly things
to make it happen. Private letters,
looking the other way on risk, building
up exposures to more and more excessive
and extreme levels. And all the time,
believing higher returns are just as
safe as not higher returns, completely
in opposition to the basic laws of
finance, which, like the credit cycle,
have not been repealed. This is how
credit cycles look, and the insurers are
right here, right in the middle of all
of it.
But of course, it's not just insurance
companies putting risky bonds or assets
in their portfolios. It goes much deeper
and gets far more complicated because of
course it does. This is modern finance,
and this is how it works. And yes, repo
is absolutely in the middle here, as
I'll get to in just a second.
Because it's never good enough just to
get a higher coupon from a high yield
bond. Why not go into repo, borrow at a
smaller rate and use the funds to
finance much of the bonds purchase. In
that case, you get the higher yield from
the asset itself, but the repo leverage
amplifies those returns into something
extra special. And if you think these
things are risk-free or close to
risk-free, they're investment-grade
rating, all the better. And it's much
easier to do when, as a life insurance
company, you've got access to tons of
high-quality collateral like US
Treasuries that are just sitting around
in regulated reserve portfolios. So,
yes, this should sound familiar to
anyone who paid attention in 2007
heading into 2008. Where the downside
really was, just look at what happened
with AIG. Now, here's a simple diagram
that was put together by the Federal
Reserve in March of last year. And
here's the gist of what that diagram
shows. Quote, "Life insurers invest
directly in risky firms through
high-yield corporate bonds and leveraged
loans, while also gaining exposure
indirectly via broad syndicated loans,
BSLs, CLOs,
uh middle-market CLOs, BDCs, the the
private credit stuff that we've been
talking about. Their funding comes from
policyholders through insurance
liability such as fixed annuities, and
from institutional investors through
non-traditional liabilities, though they
really are at this point traditional
liabilities, including funding agreement
backed securities, FHLB advances,
securities lending programs, and repo
programs." So, what does all of that
mean? All these acronyms and letters and
uh initializations?
Look at what the diagram shows on the
right side for funding these risky
assets. There are the policyholders,
those who own the annuities and and the
like, making their premium payments and
putting in upfront capital. But look
just below that, institutional investors
they call them, like the Federal Home
Loan Banks. But just below that, also
repo, securities lending. The insurance
company pledges collateral and borrow
short-term funding in repo markets to
gain the leverage on already risky
assets. And those assets are what is
shown on the left side of the diagram.
The private credit providers like Blue
Owl or other CLO vehicles, leverage loan
syndications, they take the money they
get from the insurers, which is money
the insurers got from policy holders
plus repo, and then they re-lend it to
the riskier firms, the middle market
corporate segment. But here's the thing.
Because a lot of that repo leverage is
offshore, which is a whole other topic
here, it's largely hidden. Plus the
structure obscures everything on top of
everything else. From the outside,
everything looks good, solid, steady,
limited leverage. But let's go back to
the Fed report one more time. There's a
lot of jargon in it, but all you need to
know is that the terminology simply
applies to how insurance companies
create complicated structure
just to do everything we talked about,
to juice the returns even more not
really have to show it. And that
includes setting up private credit asset
managers. Yes,
private credit asset managers themselves
within the insurance company umbrella.
And even if they are largely located and
housed offshore,
it still takes place. Here's the report.
Well, AMBDC's regulatory leverage is
under 2.1. And this is actually a an
anonymous example that the report is
drawing from.
We estimate the AMBDC's consolidated
leverage could reach up to 12 to 1 when
combined with its affiliate JFLFs,
MMCLOs, all the complicated structures
that we just went over. In effect, the
loan portfolio is funded through a mix
of debt and equity from all of these
various things, and the insurance
company itself, along with financing
from external investors, the annuity
holders. Such complex arrangements thus
obscure the true leverage of both the
insurer and the insurer affiliated asset
manager. So it looks like there's just
2:1 leverage for the asset manager, but
in reality, it could be 12 to one, but
who the hell really knows? Now, I'd
wager, just like 2008, none of those who
are doing it know either. The companies
themselves, the repo funders, nobody
really knows the extent of all this.
They just do it because the money looks
so darn good.
Now, I know what you're thinking. Could
this go too far and actually lead to
major insurance companies failing, and
what would that mean? That would be
systemic to say the least. And while
that's a small chance, it's a non-zero
chance.
So, again, it's not the big banks that
we necessarily need to be worried about.
That was all 2008. This time around, the
focus is on shadow banks and who it is
that has been shoveling all that money
to the shadows. So, while the chances of
a life insurance company failing,
they're not huge, they're there. But
just put that one on the back burner
because we're a very long way to
something like that. But if the losses
do pile up, you do have to question the
retirement assets, the annuities. The
performance is going to get impaired,
and depending upon by how much, that's
where it becomes potentially a bigger
problem as retirees might begin to
finally ask themselves some
uncomfortable questions, starting with
how were they able to generate these
wonderful returns and guarantees?
Do policyholders start to exit their
contracts? How do insurers respond to
that pressure? Those are the real
unknowns here, not what just the next
Lehman Brothers. Now, the more immediate
concerns, as I said, are repo and how
insurance companies overall are either
going to voluntarily respond to the
growing bust,
or they might be forced to react in the
ways most of them right now would rather
still not even think about. Yes, that's
collateral. And if the selling begets
more selling in private credit and
prices become further impaired, it just
raises the chances that the losses from
private credit spread out into not just
insurers, but more so their coverage,
meaning those retirement plans. But
either way, insurance,
that's the big one this time, not the
big banks. And if you couldn't tell,
the big bankers know it.
That's why they're almost giddy to be
talking about credit losses and credit
cycles this time. Meanwhile, insurance
execs, nowhere to be seen. You've got
Blue Owl out there howling about nothing
to see here, but follow the money. And
where does that money go?
To insurance companies and repo.
Now, clear on the other side of the
Pacific, another slow-motion credit
bust, maybe crisis developing over in
China that has just moved into
full-blown extended pretend and all the
details on that in the video link below.
As always, thank you very much for
joining me. Huge thank you, Eurodollar
University members and subscribers. And
until next time,
take care.